# **Ehsan Shareghi**

☑ ehsan.shareghi@gmail.com
 ⑥ eehsan.github.io
 Fields of Interest: Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning

I lead a small team of grad and undergrad students working on predictive models for language (text and speech). During my PhD and early parts of Postdoc, I worked on Bayesian nonparametric models and Bayesian learning of neural models and their application in language modelling and parsing. Since 2019 I have been working on various tasks and settings where training data is not sufficient for generalization at test or deployment due to several reasons; insufficient training data, knowledge-intensive nature of the task, absence of symbolic constraints. While in principle the solutions we investigate are agnostic to the underlying models, we try to leverage pretrained large models as much as possible. Hence, in recent years we have been also investigating various shortcomings of such models. Some recent areas of research:

- o Deep generative models (e.g., generation, semi-supervised learning, sparsity and disentanglement)
- Self-supervised learning (e.g., applications in text, speech, and graph)
- o Utilising graphs for knowledge intensive tasks (e.g., graph-to-text generation, applications in biomedical domain)
- o Probing and augmenting pretrained large models (e.g., representational and computational efficiency, reliability)
- o Bayesian learning and inference (e.g., applications in training with small data)

# **Employment**

Department of Data Science and Artificial Intelligence, Monash University

Tenured Assistant Professor in Machine Learning

Melbourne, AUS

Jan 2021–Present

Language Technology Lab, University of Cambridge

Cambridge, UK Oct 2020-Present

Affiliated Lecturer

Department of Electronic and Electrical Engineering, University College London

London, UK

Tenured Lecturer in Machine Learning

April 2020–Dec 2020

Language Technology Lab, University of Cambridge

Postdoctoral Researcher (Advisor: Anna Korhonen)

Jan 2018-April 2020

Cambridge, UK

I worked on training deep neural models in resource poor settings by compensating for the lack of labelled data via (i) developing Bayesian learning and efficient approximate inference schemes, and (ii) building on the generative capacity of deep generative models for semi-supervised learning to leverage unlabeled data, and (iii) sharing training across tasks and languages.

## **Education**

#### Faculty of Information Technology, Monash University

Melbourne, AUS Oct 2013-Oct 2017

PhD in Computer Science

Thesis: Scalable Non-Markovian Sequential Modelling for Natural Language Processing Advisors: Gholamreza Haffari, Trevor Cohn (University of Melbourne), Ann Nicholson

Internal Examiners: Wray Buntine, Ingrid Zukerman

External Examiners: Brian Roark (Google), Mark Dras (Macquarie University)

#### Department of Computer Science, Concordia University

Montreal, CA

Jan 2011-April 2013

M.Sc. in Computer Science

Thesis: Feature Combination for Measuring Sentence Similarity

Advisor: Sabine Bergler

Examiners: Adam Krzyzak (Concordia University), Leila Kosseim (Concordia University)

Department of Computer Science, Shahid Beheshti University (National University of Iran) Tehran, IR

B.Sc. in Computer Science Sept 2004–2009

Thesis: Text Summarization with Harmony Search Algorithm-Based Sentence Extraction

Advisor: Leila Sharif

# **Selected Publications**

- 2022 J. Han, E. Shareghi, Self-supervised Graph Masking Pre-training for Graph-to-Text Generation, Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)
- 2022 J. Zhao, H. Yang, G. Haffari, E. Shareghi, RedApt: Faster and Smaller Speech Translation without Quality Compromise, Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (Findings of EMNLP)
- 2022 H. Yang, J. Zhao, G. Haffari, E. Shareghi, Self-supervised Rewiring of Pre-trained Speech Encoders: Towards Faster Fine-tuning with Less Labels in Speech Processing, Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (Findings of EMNLP)
- 2022 J. Zhao, H. Yang, G. Haffari, E. Shareghi, M-Adapter: Modality Adaptation for End-to-End Speech-to-Text Translation, Proceedings of the Conference of the International Speech Communication Association (INTERSPEECH)
- 2022 Y. Su, F. Liu, Z. Meng, T. Lan, L. Shu, E. Shareghi, N. Collier, TaCL: Improving BERT Pre-training with Token-aware Contrastive Learning, Proceedings of the North American Chapter of Association for Computational Linguistics (Findings of NAACL)
- 2022 L. Zhang, W. Buntine, E. Shareghi, On the Effect of Isotropy on VAE Representations of Text, Proceedings of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
- 2022 Z. Meng, F. Liu, E. Shareghi, Y. Su, C. Collins, N. Collier, Rewire-and-Probe: A Contrastive Recipe for Probing Knowledge in Pretrained Biomedical Language Models, Proceedings of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
- 2022 D. K. Ryu, E. Shareghi, M. Fang, Y. Xu, S. Pan, G. Haffari, Fire Burns, Sword Cuts: Commonsense Inductive Bias for Exploration in Text-based Games, Proceedings of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
- 2021 Z. Meng, F. Liu, T. Clark, E. Shareghi, N. Collier, Mixture-of-Partitions: Infusing Large Biomedical Knowledge Graphs into BERT, Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)
- 2021 J. Zhao, P. Arthur, G. Haffari, T. Cohn and E. Shareghi, It Is Not As Good As You Think! Evaluating Simultaneous Machine Translation on Interpretation Data, Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)
- 2021 L. Zhang, V. Prokhorov, E. Shareghi, Unsupervised Representation Disentanglement of Text: An Evaluation on Synthetic Datasets, Proceedings of the Workshop on Representation Learning for NLP (**Rep4NLP**), 2021
- 2021 V. Prokhorov, Y. Li, E. Shareghi, N. Collier, Learning Sparse Sentence Encoding without Supervision: An Exploration of Sparsity in Variational Autoencoders. Proceedings of the Workshop on Representation Learning for NLP (Rep4NLP), 2021
- 2021 T. Clark, C. Conforti, F. Liu, Z. Meng, E. Shareghi, N. Collier, Integrating Transformers and Knowledge Graphs for Twitter Stance Detection, Proceedings of the Workshop on Noisy User-generated Text (W-NUT), 2021
- 2021 M. Zhao, Y. Zhu, E. Shareghi, I. Vulić, R. Reichart, A. Korhonen, H. Schütze, A Closer Look at Few-Shot Crosslingual Transfer: The Choice of Shots Matters, Proceedings of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
- 2021 F. Liu, E. Shareghi, Z. Meng, M. Basaldella, N. Collier, Self-alignment Pretraining for Biomedical Entity Representations, Proceedings of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL)
- 2021 Y. Zhu, E. Shareghi, Y. Li, R. Reichart, A. Korhonen, Combining Deep Generative Models and Multi-lingual Pretraining for Semi-supervised Document Classification, Proceedings of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL)
- 2020 M. Basaldella, F. Liu, E. Shareghi, N. Collier, COMETA: A Corpus for Medical Entity Linking in the Social Media, Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)
- 2019 V. Prokhorov, E. Shareghi, Y. Li, M.T. Pilehvar, N. Collier, On the Importance of the Kullback-Leibler Divergence Term in Variational Autoencoders for Text Generation, Proceedings of the Workshop on Neural Generation and Translation (WNGT), 2019
- 2019 E. Shareghi, Y. Li, Y. Zhu, R. Reichart, A. Korhonen, Bayesian Learning for Neural Dependency Parsing, Proceedings of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL)
- 2019 E. Shareghi, D. Gerz, I. Vulić, A. Korhonen, A Bit of Progress and Stronger *n*-gram Language Modeling Baselines, Proceedings of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (**NAACL**)
- 2017 E. Shareghi, G. Haffari, T. Cohn, Compressed Nonparametric (Bayesian) Language Modelling, Proceedings of the International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)
- 2016 E. Shareghi, T. Cohn, G. Haffari, Richer Interpolative Smoothing Based on Modified Kneser-Ney Language Modeling, Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)
- 2016 E. Shareghi, M. Petri, G. Haffari, T. Cohn, Fast, Small and Exact: Infinite-order Language Modelling with Compressed Suffix Trees, Transactions of the Association for Computational Linguistics (**TACL**)
- 2015 E. Shareghi, M. Petri, G. Haffari, T. Cohn, Compact, Efficient and Unlimited Capacity: Language Modeling with

Compressed Suffix Trees, Proceedings of the Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)

2015 E. Shareghi, G. Haffari, T. Cohn, A. Nicholson, Structured Prediction of Sequences and Trees using Infinite
Contexts, Proceedings of the European Conference on Machine Learning (ECML)

# **Supervisions**

Ongoing Jiuzhou Han [PhD,2023 - ], Monash University

Topic: Graph-based Generation

Ongoing Chang Shu [PhD,2023 - ], University of Cambridge (Co-Advise with Prof. Collier)

- Topic: Augmenting Large Language Models

Ongoing Yinhong Liu [PhD,2022 - ], University of Cambridge (Co-Advise with Prof. Collier)

- Topic: Guided Decoding

Ongoing Jinming Zhao [PhD,2021 - ], Monash University

- Topic: Speech Translation

Ongoing Dongwon Ryu [PhD,2021 - ], Monash University

- Topic: Reinforcement Learning and Interactive Games

Alumni Xiny Li [Honours, 2022], Monash University

- Thesis: In-Context Knowledge Elicitation from Large Language Models

Alumni Hao Yang [Msc, 2022], Monash University

- Thesis: Self-supervised Rewiring for Faster Fine-tuning with Less Labels in Speech Understanding Tasks

Alumni Yi Zhu [PhD,2019-2022], University of Cambridge (Co-Advise with Prof. Korhonen)

- Thesis: Multi-Lingual Learning with Few Labels

Alumni Jirarote Jirasirikul [MSc,2021], Monash University

- Thesis: Fine-tuning Pretrained Language Models for Biomedical Tasks

Alumni Victor Prokhorov [PhD,2019-2021], University of Cambridge (Co-Advise with Prof. Collier)

- Thesis: Injecting Inductive Biases into Distributed Representations of Text

Alumni Aiswarya Kaladharan [MSc,2020], UCL

- Thesis: Privacy-Preserving Neural Representation for Audio Speech

Alumni Lan Zhang [MSc,2020], UCL

- Thesis: Towards Understanding the Latent Space in Variational Autoencoders

Alumni Lei Yang [MSc,2020], UCL

- Thesis: Deep Neural Models for Generating Recipes

#### **Grants**

- Tracking media and parliamentary narratives around cycles of disadvantage in Australia (AUD 500k), Chief Investigator, Paul Ramsay Foundation (2022-2023)
- o Big Idea Fund (AUD 50k), Chief Investigator, Monash University (2021)
- o Research Gift (USD 5k), Adobe Research (2021)
- o Early Career Grant (AUD 15k), Monash University (2021)
- o Research Gift (USD 5k), Adobe Research (2019)

# **Teaching**

- Natural Language Processing (FIT5217), Monash University, 2022, 2023
- Data Analysis for Semi-structured Data (FIT5212), Monash University, 2022, 2023
- o Applied Machine Learning II (ELEC0135), Co-Lecturer, UCL, 2020
- o Quantitative Methods in Analyzing Linguistic Data (QMALD), University of Cambridge, 2020
- o Computational Linguistics (Li18), Guest Lecturer, University of Cambridge, 2018, 2019

## **Talks**

On the Limits of Large Neural Language Models

Venue: The 1st Monash Interdisciplinary Workshop on Language.

Utilising the Unlabelled Text via Deep Generative Models

Venue: Monash ML Seminars.

Melbourne, AUS November 2022

Melbourne, AUS March 2021

- / -

Language Modelling: Something Old, Something New London, UK 0 Venue: UCL Engineering Dept. February 2020 Modeling Solutions for Low-resource Parsing Cambridge, UK Venue: Apple Siri Lab October 2018 Scalable Non-Markovian Language Modeling Cambridge, UK Venue: DTAL, University of Cambridge April 2018 Scalable and Unbounded Smoothing for Language Modeling Melbourne, AUS December 2016 Venue: Australasian Language Technology Association (ALTA) **Unbounded Smoothing for NLP (Trees and Sequences)** Melbourne, AUS Venue: IBM Research Australia September 2016

## **Internships**

IBM Research
Part-Time Research Intern

IBM Research
Part-Time Research Intern

Part-Time Research Intern

Melbourne, AUS
Melbourne, AUS

Full-Time Research Intern

2015–2015

## **PhD Theses Examinations**

o Multilingual Representations and Models for Improved Low-Resource Language Processing, Masoud Jalili Sabet (LMU, Advisor: Hinrich Schütze), 2022

## **Technical and Personal skills**

- Programming Languages: Python, C++ (and some Shell)
- Natural Language Processing: GATE API, CoreNLP, NLTK, SpaCy
- o Machine Learning/Statistics tools: PyTorch, DyNet, R, Scikit, Weka API
- o Languages: Persian (Native), English (Fluent), Turkish-Azeri (Fluent)

## **Services**

- Organization: Area Chair of Multilinguality Track in EACL2023, General Chair of The 1st Monash Interdisciplinary Workshop on Language 2022, General Chair of The 3rd DeepLo2022 Workshop (co-located with NAACL22), Assistant for General Chairs of ACL2019
- Invited to Review for: TACL, ACL, EMNLP, NAACL, ARR Rolling Review, AAAI, IJCAI, CONLL, COLING
- Theater: Dramaturge in Monash University Student Theater (2014)